Thank you.
谢谢。
Okay, good afternoon, good morning, good evening, good night, wherever you are,
好的，下午好，早上好，傍晚好，晚上好，无论你在哪里，
so today I want to talk about the zookeeper
所以今天我想谈谈 zookeeper ，
and with the this background,
以及它的背景，
paper that we you know which is assigned for today,
我们今天布置的论文，
which is from 2010.
是 2010 年的。
And, so there's gonna be referring back the last couple lectures,
所以我们会回顾上几节课的内容，
I think we dove in quite a bit of detail into raft,
我想我们在 raft 上了解相当多的细节，
including looking at code,
包括查看代码，
the lectures from now on are going to be more conceptual
从现在开始的课程将更加概念化，
and exploring ideas in distributed systems zookeeper's,
探索分布式系统 zookeeper 的想法，
and the zookeeper, what is particularly relevant to us,
而 zookeeper 是与我们有关系的，
because it has a little bit of relationship
因为它有一点关系
as we'll see with lab 3.
正如我们将在实验 3 中看到的。
And so it will allow us to talk about some properties of lab 3,
所以，它允许我们讨论实验 3 的一些属性，
and particularly linearizability,
特别是线性一致性，
but zookeeper system more importantly,
但 zookeeper 更重要的，
it's interesting,
它很有趣，
because one of widely-used system in practice,
因为它是一个在实践中广泛使用的系统，
well beyond Apache, well beyond Yahoo,
来自 Apache ，来自雅虎，
is a open source Apache project,
是一个开源的 Apache 项目，
that is still active.
它仍然是活跃的。
What particularly interesting about it for us,
对我们来说特别有趣的是，
in the lecture like today is actually high performance,
在今天这样的课程中，是高性能，
and high performance, I mean,
高性能，我的意思是，
much higher performance than what actually lab 3 is gonna be.
比实验 3 要高得多的性能。
I'll talk to talk quite a bit of detail about this,
关于这一点，我会详细地谈一谈，
and there's sort of two reasons why it is high performance,
它之所以高性能，有两个原因，
one, it is the client operations are asynchronous,
一个是，它的客户端操作是异步的，
and really what high performing from here means is,
这里高性能的意思是，
we can, the system can process many more operations per second,
系统每秒可以处理更多的操作，
so it's really a throughput metric,
所以它是一个吞吐量指标，
and the second reason it's high performances because,
第二个高性能的原因是，
it doesn't provide strong consistency,
它没有提供强一致性，
so it doesn't, it has an interesting consistency definition,
它有一个有趣的一致性定义，
and it gives us some freedom
它给了我们一些自由
to execute basically read operations on any replica,
可以在任何复制上执行读取操作，
and therefore read [] can scale.
因此读取[]是可以扩展的。
Then, the second aspect that is interesting from zookeeper is,
然后 zookeeper 有趣的第二个方面是，
in addition to being high performance,
除了高性能之外，
it is sort of a generic,
它是一种通用的，
what they call coordination service,
他们称之为协调服务，
and the point being here is,
这里的重点是，
there are many applications,
有很多应用程序，
where you need to keep track of like who's part of this cluster
你需要跟踪哪些是这个集群的一部分，
and who's the master,
以及谁是 master ，
so think about the mapreduce or think about the GFS,
所以想想 mapreduce 或 GFS ，
the master in GFS needs to keep track
GFS 中的 master 需要跟踪
or like for every chunk,
或者每个块，
who are the servers that actually server that,
谁是服务的服务器，
[] server chunk who servers actually is the master,
那个服务块是 master ，
and so tracking that sort of configuration information,
所以跟踪配置信息，
you know comes up in lots of different distributed applications,
来自许多不同的分布式应用程序中，
zookeeper is really designed to support that kind of thing,
zookeeper 是为了支持这种东西而设计的，
so you sort of outsource all the configuration management to zookeeper,
所以你可以把所有的配置管理交给 zookeeper ，
and then focus the rest of your application development,
然后专注于你的应用程序其他部分的开发，
on other aspects of your distributed system.
你的分布式系统的其他方面。
Okay, so that's sort of a brief introduction,
好的，这是一个简短的介绍，
you know the topics that we're gonna be talking about.
我们要讨论的话题。
And as usual, feel free to interrupt at any time,
像往常一样，你可以随时打断我，
or you know post something in the chat message,
或者在聊天中发布一些东西，
let me actually pull up the chat.
让我来调出聊天。
Okay, so we just you know start from the basics zookeeper is replicated state machine,
好的，我们从 zookeeper 的基础开始，复制状态机，
in the same way that you know the replicated state machines that we've been seeing.
像我们所看到的复制状态机一样。
And so let's draw the usual picture,
所以，让我们来画一个通常的图，
we have some servers,
我们有一些服务器，
in this case,
在这种情况下，
it's gonna be zookeeper ZK.
它将是 zookeeper ZK 。
It receives requests from clients,
它接收来自客户端的请求，
that create create znode,
创建 znode ，
and basically the way it interacts to distribute these operations,
它分发这些操作的方式，
it has sort of a separate library,
它有一个独立的库，
you know think about this as the raft library,
把这个想象成跟 raft 库类似，
in their case, it's called ZAB.
在他们的情况下，它被称为 ZAB 。
Basically, you know the leader you know sticks the operation into
基本上，领导者把操作放入
you know the equivalent raft library,
相当于 raft 库的地方，
that you know talks you know to you know other libraries or other peers,
与其他库或其他节点进行交互，
that basically creates a log,
这创建一个日志，
you know that conveys with all these operations and all these machines,
通过所有这些操作和这些机器，
and then the operations are the log of feedback to the [],
然后操作的日志返回给[]，
so in our case, the apply channel to the service,
在我们的示例中，通过 apply channel 给服务，
the service applies the operation in response to the client,
服务应用该操作以响应客户端，
and so we have basically different [] is running.
所以，我们有不同的[]在运行。
And so far, you know in the labs you know really focusing mostly,
到目前为止，在实验里，主要专注于，
you know lab 2 is all about you know this part,
实验 2 是关于这一部分，
implementing in our case raft, so instead of ZAB,
在我们的示例中，实现 raft ，而不是 ZAB ，
and for the first or the at a very high level,
从一个很高的级别来看，
you can think about ZAB being another raft,
你可以把 ZAB 当成另一个 raft ，
you know providing sort of similar guarantees
提供类似的保证，
you know implemented quite differently,
但是实现方式不同，
you know it provides an order of all the operations,
它提供了所有操作的顺序，
the [] failures, network partitions, etc etc,
[]故障，网络分区等等，
doesn't suffer from split-brain brain,
不会有脑裂的问题，
all are sort of things which we associate with the raft library.
都是与 raft 库联系在一起的东西。
In you know what we're gonna be focusing in lab 3 on is,
我们在实验 3 要关注的是，
actually implementing a service on top of it,
在它上面实现一个服务，
so this paper talks about the this coordination service zookeeper in,
这篇论文讨论的了 zookeeper 协调服务，
we're going to actually implement in lab 3 key value stores,
我们将在实验 3 中实现键值存储，
and the data structure is just map from keys to values.
数据结构只是从键到值的映射。
And so the operations you know that we're going to be supporting are put and get,
所以我们在那里支持的操作是 put 和 get ，
so the clients may put and get operations you know to the service,
所以客户端可能发送 put get 操作给服务，
the service runs in through raft,
服务通过 raft 运行，
and then applies them one by one to the key value store.
然后将它们逐个应用到键值存储。
In zookeeper you know the structures slightly different,
在 zookeeper 中，结构略有不同，
there's a tree of znodes,
这里有一个 znode 组成的树，
but the basic operation is the applys the same,
但基本的操作是应用相同的，
you know the lower layer the ZAB or the ZAB library
下层的 ZAB 库，
or ZAB library orders all the operations,
ZAB 库对所有操作进行排序，
they're applied in the same order all replicas,
以相同的顺序应用到所有的副本，
because they are applied all in the same order,
因为它们都以相同的顺序应用，
there's no non-determinism,
没有非确定性的（操作），
the resulting state on each of the replica is going to be identical.
每个副本上的结果状态将是相同的。
Okay?
好的?
That's sort of the basic setting of this paper,
这是这篇论文的基本背景，
and sort of also the relation, part of the relationship
也是它们之间的关系，
between lab 3 and the zookeeper service itself.
实验 3 和 zookeeper 服务之间的（关系）。
And mostly going to be talking in this lecture
在这节课中，主要讨论的是
on focus on the zookeeper part itself,
关注 zookeeper 本身，
and not talk about ZAB,
不讨论 ZAB ，
because you're gonna assume,
因为你会认为，
that's similar to what we're doing and we're doing in lab 2.
它和我们在实验 2 做的事情很相似。
Okay, we're going to talking a little bit about,
好的，我们稍微谈谈，
what kind of performance would you observe,
你会看到什么样的性能，
if you want to finish lab 3,
如果完成实验 3 ，
and would measure how many you puts or gets your operation get through per second,
并且测量每秒通过的 put 或 get 操作，
because one of the achievements this paper is you know high performance.
因为这篇论文的一个成功就是高性能。
So let's think a little bit about that,
所以让我们稍微想一想，
so let's assume you know a put operation coming in,
我们假设有一个 put 操作进来，
and you know put operation comes in by the leader,
并且 put 操作是由领导者进来的，
and so we're just gonna go for the normal case,
所以我们选择正常的情况，
like the standard case, where everything is working,
比如标准的情况，一切都正常，
no network failures, no partitions, nothing,
没有网络故障，分区，没有任何事情，
everything works out perfectly.
一切都很完美。
Here's the leader,
这是领导者，
we've got two followers.
我们有两个跟随者。
And you know now you know that protocol you know probably inside out,
现在可能协议[完全地]，
you know the first thing of course it happens,
第一件事当然是，
like would be the leader call start,
领导者调用 start ，
start actually writes the put operation to its, to log in the leader,
start 写入 put 操作到领导者的日志，
and then the leader you know propagates it's log to the other followers,
然后领导者将它的日志传播给其他跟随者，
and you know before it actually happens in parallel,
在它并行发生前，
send that argument,
发送那个参数，
let me draw it slightly differently,
让我稍微重画一下，
basically it launches a bunch of RPCs almost instantaneously to the different followers,
它几乎同时向不同的跟随者发出一系列 RPC ，
each follower of course you know will append the entry to its logs,
当然，每个跟随者将条目附加到它的日志中，
so that requires a writes to persistent storage,
所以需要向持久存储写入，
same thing here,
这里也是一样的，
and then they respond back.
然后它们会做出响应。
And so here's a response back,
所以这是响应，
and in this case, majority has responded,
在这种情况下，大多数都做出了响应，
the leader can actually apply the operation,
领导者可以接受操作，
so the leader will actually apply the operation here for [],
领导者在这里对[]应用操作，
so do the put and send the response back to the client.
执行 put 并将响应发送回客户端。
What curious about is like,
令人好奇的是，
how many put per second can we actually get,
我们每秒能得到多少次 put ，
you know in this in this setting.
在这个背景下。
And you know think about it,
考虑一下，
you know the when you do [] back-of-the-envelope-calculation,
当你做[]估算，
we don't really care exactly about the exact numbers,
我们并不关心确切的数字，
but you know one roundtrip,
但是一次往返，
we need at least one roundtrip to actually get the majority,right,
我们至少需要一次往返才能找到大多数，
leader needs to talk to at least one follower to actually maintain the majority,
领导者需要与至少一个访问跟随者以保持多数，
so we're going to have at least one roundtrip messaging.
所以，我们至少需要一条往返消息。
And then you sort of need to look at the writes to stable storage,
然后，你需要看对稳定存储的写入，
because those tend to be expensive,
因为那些往往很昂贵，
and we'll see you know in this case,
在这种情况下，我们会看到，
we're going to have two writes,
我们将有两次写入，
because there's gonna be one write at the leader,
因为会有一个写入到领导者，
one write at the follower,
一次写入到跟随者，
at that point, we have at least two nodes that have copy,
在这一点上，我们至少有两个节点具有副本，
so what are the things will be committed,
所以那个消息将会提交，
if no further failures,
如果没有更多故障，
and so basically you know 2, and minimum we're going to need 2 writes.
所以至少我们需要 2 次写入。
So that's sort of the base and the best you could do right,
所以这是你能做的最好的，
in this simple scheme that we discussed, discussed here,
在我们在这里讨论的这个简单的方案中，
sort of, we can think about the cost is,
在某种程度上，我们可以考虑成本是多少，
in a roundtrip,
在一个往返中，
you know maybe those running in the data center,
也许这些运行在数据中心，
networks are not across the Internet,
网络不通过互联网，
maybe you know that actually comes down to 1 millisecond,
这个可以降到 1 毫秒，
we're roughly in the [neighborhood] for a millisecond,
我们大概在附近 1 毫秒，
maybe a little bit faster,
可能会快一点，
but we don't really care about,
但我们并不关心，
just a millisecond.
只是使用 1 毫秒。
So, we're going to do two writes to stable storage,
我们将行两次写入到稳定存储，
write actually to stable storage seems to be expensive,
写入稳定存储似乎很昂贵，
and you know depends on what medium, what technology you're using for stable storage,
取决于使用什么介质和什么技术来做稳定存储，
let's assume when we're using SSDs, you know sort of pretty typical,
假设我们使用固态硬盘，这是很典型的，
then you know presumably one write in the order of maybe 2 milliseconds,
那么可能一次顺序写入需要 2 毫秒，
you know we've got to really make sure actually the write ends up on the in the SSD,
我们必须确保写入最终会在固态硬盘，
so we're gonna probably has to be a synchronous write,
所以，我们可能必须进行同步写入，
so it means like 2 milliseconds for one write,
所以这意味着一次写入需要 2 毫秒，
so two writes would be roughly you know 4 milliseconds.
所以两次写入大约是 4 毫秒。
So we ended up, there's going to be 5 milliseconds.
所以我们结束了，将有 5 毫秒。
And so, how many operations per second?
那么，每秒有多少次操作？
Just to see if anybody still awake.
只是想看看有没有人还醒着。
200.
200 。
Yeah, so there's gonna be 200 put per second.
是的，所以每秒会有 200 次 put 。
Any questions about this, does that make sense?
对这个有什么问题吗，能理解吗？
Okay, so now let's look at zookeeper.
好的，现在让我们来看看 zookeeper 。
What's the roundtrip for in the writes,
写入的往返是什么，
sorry, I missed it.
抱歉，我错过了。
The, the writes, the writes there's you know roundtrip,
写入没有往返，
there's 1 roundtrip correct,
有一个往返，
talk from the leader to the follower,
领导者访问跟随者，
and the two writes,
以及两个写入，
one at the stable storage for the leader
一个是在领导的稳定存储，
and one at the stable storage for the follower,
一个是在跟随者的稳定存储，
and the 2 writes end up to 4,
两次写入最终是 4 ，
roundtrip to roughly 1 millisecond,
往返大约 1 毫秒，
so the total is 5 milliseconds for one put.
所以一次 put 的总计是 5 毫秒。
Okay, let's look at the zookeeper,
好的，让我们来看看 zookeeper ，
and again the metric that the paper is interested in is the throughput metric,
再说一次，论文感兴趣的指标是吞吐量指标，
where it basically the clients, you have many many many clients
你有很多客户端，
and they pump many request to zookeeper as much as possible
它们发出很多请求到 zookeeper ，
and [pipeline] them aggressively.
并积极地[输送]它们。
And so, so let's see what the results of that is,
让我们来看看结果是什么，
and so let me pull up the graph of the paper,
所以让我拿出论文的图，
and you know look at that paper a little, look the graph a little bit.
稍微看一下论文，这张图。
So a couple things that presumably to observe,
有几件事应该是要注意的，
you know on the x axis is the percentage of read requests,
x 轴上是读请求百分比，
as we'll see in a second,
我们很快会看到，
you know this is going to be important to distinguish read or write operations,
区分读操作或写操作非常重要，
and so write operations are really operations that modify,
写操作是修改的操作，
any write operation that modifies state,
任何写操作都会修改状态，
read operations are operations don't modify the state at all,
读操作是完全不修改状态的操作，
so in our lab three terms,
在我们实验的三个术语中，
you know put would be the write operation
put 是写操作，
and get be the read operation.
get 是读操作。
And on the y axis is the number operations per second,
在 y 轴上是每秒的操作次数，
and let's look at the case of 3 servers,
让我们来看看 3 台服务器的情况，
and so the first thing you notice is that zero reads,
你注意到的第一件事是没有读，
so only write operations, so what that modify the state,
只有写操作，它会修改状态，
you know we get roughly 21k operations per second as throughput, right,
我们得到大约每秒 21k 次操作的吞吐量，
and you know look at, you know if the system only has reads,
如果系统只有读，
it actually gets a lot more,
它得到了更多，
and gets up in the you know whatever the 60-70 reads region,
到达 60-70 的区域，
and in fact, what really go on is,
实际上发生的是，
that the number reads,
读次数，
the throughput in terms of reads the scales with the number of servers.
读吞吐量与服务器数量成正比。
So, if you have 3 servers,
所以，如果你有 3 台服务器，
you know you get 3 times you know the read performance of one server,
你可以得到一台服务器的读性能的 3 倍，
if you have 5 servers,
如果你有 5 台服务器，
you get 5 times the read performance one server.
你可以得到一台服务器的读性能的 5 倍。
Of course not true writes, correct,
当然对于写不是这样的，
in fact if you look at this graph,
如果你看这张图，
you see that if with more servers,
你可以看到，如果有更多的服务器，
the write performance actually goes down.
写入性能实际上会下降。
And you know that the reason for that is presumably,
这样的原因大概是，
the leader has to chat with more servers,
领导者必须访问更多服务器，
to actually gets operation through.
让操作可以通过。
And so when we're purely doing write operations,
所以，当我们只进行写操作时，
we actually limited,
我们是有限的，
and we cannot expect more performance than a single server,
我们不能期望比单台服务器更高的性能，
in fact, the [up] servers we're going to go down performance.
实际上，增加服务器将降低性能。
And so this 21k you know per second,
所以，这个 21k 每秒，
you know even for single,
即使对于单台（服务器），
for you know write operations with a configuration of 3 servers,
对于配置 3 台服务器的写操作，
you know is impressive number,
是一个令人印象深刻的数字，
is quite a bit higher than actually the simple [] that we did for lab 3,
比我们在实验 3 中的简单[]要高得多，
lab 3 will never get the, will not get closer to the number at all.
实验 3 完全不会靠近这个数字。
And so we want to understand,
所以我们想要了解，
you want to see in this design,
你想在这个设计中看到，
what the designer do to actually get that kind of performance.
设计者做了什么，获得这样的性能。
And sort of two as I mentioned earlier,
我之前提到的，
there's sort of two key ideas,
有两个关键的想法，
1, everything is asynchronous,
1 ，任何东西都是异步的，
or the clients can submit many operations to raft or zookeeper, sorry, in a single shot,
或者客户端可以一次向 zookeeper 提交多个操作，
so they all pipeline,
它们排队，
so basically when, the way to think about zookeeper client,
考虑 zookeeper 客户端的方式，
basically says, please start executing this put
说，请开始执行这个 put ，
and doesn't wait in the response of the put,
但是不等待 put 的响应，
you know immediately issues the second put,
直接发送第二个 put ，
and then the third and fourth [and fifth],
然后是第三个，第四个，第五个，
so, for example, a lot of these puts run will be batched together,
比如，很多 put 放在一起，
maybe even a single message will be transferred to the leader,
也许只有一条消息传递给领导者，
and the leader will apply them all at the same time,
领导者将同时应用所有它们，
in fact, will leader will write to the persistent storage only once,
事实上，领导者只向持久久存储写入一次，
you know for a whole batch of operation,
对于批量的操作，
so instead of having one write per operation,
所以，不是每个操作一次写入，
you're going to have one disk write to many many many operations,
而是多个操作一次磁盘写入，
and this is one reason,
这是一个原因，
you know they get this very good performance on write operations.
他们在写入操作上获得非常好的性能。
And the second thing is,
第二件事是，
they do something special for read operations,
他们为读操作做了一些特殊的事情，
they allow read operations to be processed by any server.
他们允许读操作在任何服务器处理。
So instead of running all the operations through the leader,
所以，不是通过领导者来执行所有的操作，
they allow operations to actually be processed by any server.
他们允许任何服务器处理操作。
So.
所以。
And then the [] we want to talk a little bit more about it.
我们想要更多地谈论它。
I think, I wanted to think about what could we do something similar,
我想我们可以做些类似的事情，
like, let's say we want to lab 3,
比如，我们想要在实验 3 中做的，
and we're gonna do the same trick,
我们做相同的事，
here we want to look at is
这里我们想要的是
basically reads from any machine or any peer.
从任何机器或任何节点读取。
So the picture would be as follows,
所以，图片如下所示，
you know we have a leader,
我们有一个领导者，
we have the two followers,
我们有两个跟随者，
we just stick to the case of three,
我们使用 3 个节点的情况，
we have a client.
我们有一个客户端。
And we're like consider what actually could happen,
我们考虑可能发生的事情，
if you know we sort of, if we follow this strategy,
如果我们遵循这个策略，
where we're going to read from anything,
我们将从任何地方阅读，
we use our client,
我们使用客户端，
the leaders actually when we do puts,
领导者当我们执行 put 时，
you know they all go through the leader,
它们都通过领导者，
and so the client you know basically does read,
客户端执行读取，
and let's say you know this was a put done,
假设这个 put 已经完成，
and at the same time, roughly after after the put was done,
与此同时，几乎在 put 完成时，
the client issues a get,
客户端发出一个 get ，
and talks to one of the followers an arbitrary one,
并访问任意一个跟随者，
let's use this in case, it does not talk to the leader,
我们使用这个，它没有访问领导者，
and then you know where the follower response,
然后跟随者回应，
and the question is like what value does the get to observe.
问题是， get 观察到的值是什么。
So what are the possible values you know that the client can observe,
那么客户端可能得到的值是什么，
let's say that you know we're reading whatever the key x,
比如，我们读取键 x ，
and the initial value of x is 0,
x 的初始值是 0 ，
and this put actually put x to 1.
而这个 put 使 x 变为 1 。
And what are the value that x actually return,
那么 x 返回的值是什么，
if we don't do anything particularly special.
如果我们不做任何特别的事情。
So just a question here about the setup,
所以有一个关于设置的问题，
so if we're assuming that raft is the infrastructure here,
所以如果我们假设 raft 是这里的基础设施，
and get its just another command,
而 get 是另一个命令，
then would the follower just redirect applying to the leader,
那么跟随者会不会将应用重定向到领导者，
put or get request to the leader.
put 或 get 请求到领导者。
No, [] a lot of things we could do,
不，[]，我们可以做的事情很多，
but like we want to get this [perfect] scalability,
但我们想要获得这种完美的可扩展性，
so to get perfect scalability,
所以，为了获得完美的可扩展性，
the follower cannot talk to the leader for read operations,
对于读操作，跟随者不能访问领导者，
so basically read operations are executed by the individual followers immediately,
所以读操作是由单个跟随者直接执行的，
with that no communication,
没有沟通，
with that you know the way we're going to get perfect scalability.
我们获得完美的可扩展性。
So, there not even communicating with.
所以，这里甚至没有通信。
Yep, I'm just doing beneath plan,
是的，我只是在按计划行事，
looks like our goal is to get perfect scalability,
我们的目标是获得完美的可扩展性，
like you know zookeeper does,
就像 zookeeper 所做的，
and we want to understand like you know is that difficult or easy,
我们想要理解的这是困难的还是容易的，
or what does that really mean,
或者这到底是什么意思，
and so the first thing to find experiment is,
所以，首先要做的是，
like would do absolutely nothing at the leaders and followers,
领导者和跟随者什么都不做，
followers get read operation executed and return the value.
跟随者执行读操作并返回值。
And what can you know,
什么能，
so another question,
所以另一个问题是，
what values can be returned by, in the client observe, in this picture.
这张图中，客户端可以观察到什么值。
Can be either,
可以是任何一种，
because maybe you put,
因为可能你执行 put ，
then they make it through the disk of the leader yet.
然后它们会通过领导者的磁盘。
Yeah, it could be either,
是的，它可以是任何一种，
so either going to return 0 or it could return 1, right.
所以要么返回 0 ，要么返回 1 。
So it can return stale data, it's possibility.
所以它可能返回过时的数据。
Let's say, let's say we do,
假设我们做，
let's say return 1,
假设返回 1 ，
so this get returns 1 for a [] experiment,
对于[]实验，这个 get 返回 1 ，
and then the client does another get,
然后客户端执行另一个 get ，
now going to say to where that get is going,
现在 get 会得到什么，
but you know and what values could we see,
但是，我们可以看到什么值，
for respond to that get.
对这个 get 的回应。
Assuming there are no other writes that should be 1, right.
假设没有其他写入，这应该是 1 ，对吧。
Yeah, [unfortunately],
是的，不幸的是，
because I have 3 servers,
因为我有 3 台服务器，
if I have 5 servers?
如果我有 5 台服务器呢？
Why is it different?
为什么会不同？
Okay, let's make it different.
好的，我们让它不同。
So certainly can return 1, we're agreeing that,
所以肯定会返回 1 ，我们同意，
because if the follower talks to the second get request,
因为如果跟随者响应第二个 get 请求，
you know talks to a follower that actually has seen the put operation,
访问一个看到过 put 操作的跟随者，
which the majority of them have seen put operation,
它们中的大多数都看到过 put 操作，
we're going to get 1 back, right.
我们会到到 1 ，对吧。
The real question is, could it see 0,
真正的问题是，它能不能看到 0 ，
even though it observed the 1 earlier.
尽管它早些时候观察到了 1 。
I mean you could see that 0,
我想你可以看到 0 ，
even in the case of a 3 servers, right,
即使在 3 台服务器的情况下，
because let's say that you have the majority of servers.
因为假设你拥有大多数服务器。
Let me do first 5 case, because it's simpler to see.
让我来做前 5 个的情况，因为它更容易看到。
Are we assuming that the client always asks the same peer?
我们是否假设客户端总是请求相同的节点？
No, there might be a little network partition or disconnection for a brief period of time,
不，可能会有一小段时间的网络分区或断线，
so you don't actually have to talk to the same peer as the last time, right.
所以你不需要访问上次一样的节点，对吧。
Yeah, so in that case, it can talk to a different peer,
是的，所以在这种情况下，它可以访问不同的节点，
who and that peer may respond with 0, that's.
那个节点可能返回 0 。
So, this is possible,
所以，这是可能的，
so we're gonna have sort of strange behavior,
所以我们会有一些奇怪的行为，
in this configuration where you might see a recent,
在这配置中，你可能会看到最近的，
you know in the first case,
在第一种情况下，
we might see actually a recent value,
我们可能会看到最近的值，
and then we read actually something from back back in time.
然后我们读到一些过去的东西。
Yep.
是的。
So we're doing nothing special,
所以我们没做什么特别的事，
and just like naively read from any peer,
只是天真地从任何节点读取，
and you know we have sort of two side [types] of problems
我们有两种不同[类型]的问题，
I mean the get can return stale data,
get 可以返回过时的数据，
the get return data you've gone back in time.
get 返回过去的数据。
And so.
所以。
Sorry, wasn't this possible also with 3 followers,
抱歉，这不是 3 个跟随者也可能的吗，
because the majority was the leader and one follower
因为大多数是领导者和一个跟随者，
and you could ask the other one.
你可以访问另一个（跟随者）。
If you've seen the one in,
如果你见过那个，
yes, it could be possible, absolutely,
是的，这绝对是有可能的，
the 3 will be possible too,
3 个也是可能的，
I think the 5 is much more clear,
我认为 5 要更清楚，
that this is possible.
这是可能的。
Okay, so.
好的，所以。
So, now we're going to go back
所以，现在我们要回去，
and sort of think about a little bit of this behavior,
稍微考虑一下这种行为，
you know the returning those values, is that okay?
返回那些值，可以吗？
And this is a very interesting question,
这是一个非常有趣的问题，
and it depends of course, what do you mean with correct.
这取决于你说的正确是什么意思。
And what you know if something's okay,
如果某件事是正确的，
depends on what our correct definition is.
取决于我们的正确定义是什么。
And the correctness definition that we sort of in peddling
我们所说的正确性的定义，
for the last couple lectures at the beginning of term,
在学期开始的前几节课中，
is this notion of linearizability.
是线性一致性的概念。
And, in roughly what that means,
它的意思是，
I talked a little bit about it in a week ago,
我在一周前谈过这件事，
you know behaves like a single machine,
行为像一台机器，
that's the intuition that we've been using since the beginning of the semester,
这是我们从学期开始一直使用的直觉，
but you know the definition of linearizability is a little bit more precise,
但是线性一致性的定义要更精确一点，
sort of tries to nail down what it means to behave like a single machine,
试图确定像一台机器是什么意思，
and so when something behaves like a single machine,
所以，当某个东西表现得像一台机器时，
first of all, it has to be the case,
首先，必须是这样的情况，
that even if the operation actually concurrently,
即使操作实际上同时进行，
you can sort of order them in a total order,
你可以按整体顺序对它们进行排序，
so it's possible to construct a total order of all the operations,
所以，可以构建所有操作的整体顺序，
because in the end, it's a single machine,
因为归根结底，这是一台机器，
so it behaves as a single machine,
它的行为像一台机器，
there's only one machine,
只有一台机器，
so virtual machine that can actually perform the operations total order of ops,
虚拟机器可以以整体顺序执行操作，
and there has to be some properties true about that total order.
关于整体顺序有一些属性是真的。
And so one property that has to be true is,
所以，一个必须为真的属性是，
that the order matches real-time,
顺序与真实时间匹配，
and the real-time really what I mean is that,
真实时间我的意思是，
if operation completed before another one started,
如果操作在另一个开始前完成，
then you know that first operation has to go before the second operation in the total order.
那么，在整体顺序中，第一个操作必须在第二个操作之前。
And then there's third property,
然后是第三个属性，
that read operation, read op returns value of last write.
读操作返回最后写入的值。
That's sort of the official definition of linearizability
这是线性一致性的官方定义，
and you can just think about this
你可以认为这是
as sort of more precise definition, more precise statement,
一种更精确的定义，更准确的表述，
this first thing this intuition,
对于第一个直觉，
namely the whole thing behaves like a single machine.
也就是整个行为像一台机器。
Now we want to go back,
现在我们回来，
and you know think a little bit about scenario,
想一下这种场景，
that we [] have just on this whiteboard,
刚才在白板上的，
namely use two cases of stale data and back in time,
也就是两种情况，过时的数据和时间回退，
and think about that think whether linearizability allows them.
想想线性一致性是否允许它们。
And so let's first focus on the first one,
所以，我们首先关注第一个问题，
so we have a client 1, correct, for this,
所以我们有一个客户端 1 ，
the way you would draw this out,
你把它画出来的方式，
and reasonable linearizability is,
合理的线性一致性是，
you could draw a diagram for this form,
你可以使用这种形式画一张图，
where going to the left bar is the start of the operation,
左边是操作的开始，
the right bar is acknowledgement to the client that the operation actually executed,
右边是对执行操作的客户端的确认，
and in this case,
在这种情况下，
you know we sort of saying were to put to x and put the value of 1.
比如 put 到 x ， put 值 1 。
Then we had another client or in the same client,
然后我们有另一个客户端或者同一个客户端，
let's do drawing other client,
我们画其他客户端，
you know basically did the read,
执行读取，
and the read started well past the put operations,
读取在 put 操作之后很久才开始，
there's a get of x,
有一个 get x ，
and we had one case, where the get that's actually return the 0,
我们有一种情况，get 返回 0 ，
that was the first possibility.
这是第一种可能性。
And so that's what actually happened on the previous board,
这就是上一张白板发生的事情，
and now we want to think about this,
现在我们想考虑一下，
is this execution allowed by linearizability,
这种执行是线性一致性允许的吗，
this is the correctness definition that we're looking for,
这是我们正在寻找的正确性的定义，
then we want to see this execution,
然后我们看这个执行，
this order of operations that happened in practice,
实际发生的操作的顺序，
you know at least we've seen that it's possible in practice,
至少我们看这在实践中是可能的，
is this allowed by linearizability,
这是线性一致性允许的吗，
that is our correctness criteria.
是不是我们的正确性标准。
Is this allow by linearizability?
这是线性一致性允许的吗？
No.
不是。
No, why not?
不，为什么不是？
Well, because the C2 client operation started after the C1 completed,
因为 C2 操作是在 C1 完成之后开始的，
so in the total order,
所以在整体顺序中，
you have that put x 1
你有 put x 1 ，
and get x has to be 1,
所以 get x 必须是 1 ，
because it should read the last write.
因为它应该读取最后一次写入。
Yeah, so basically in the total order that you construct,
是的，所以在构建的整体顺序中，
you know this guy,
这个（操作），
you know this operation must be after that operation,
这个操作必须在那个操作之后，
because it started later.
因为它开始得比较晚。
But then you look, you know that violated rule number 3, correct,
你可以看到，这违反了规则 3 ，
that operation returns the value of the last write,
操作返回最后一次写入的值，
that's actually not the case,
实际上并不是这样，
actually returns [new] earlier value,
返回的是前面的值，
so this is not linearizable.
所以这是不可线性化的。
Does that make sense?
这能理解吗？
And of course it's totally matches our intuition, right,
当然，这完全符合我们的直觉，
because a single machine just could not have happened,
因为任何一台机器都不可能发生，
you know you wrote a value to a single machine,
你写入一个值到一台机器，
and then you read it back
然后你再读取，
and it's certainly not other value,
它肯定不是其他值，
it's actually the previous value,
而是之前的值，
so this is not allow.
所以这是不允许的。
Okay, let's do a second one, like other examples,
好的，让我们再看另一个示例，
so we had a client 1 again,
所以我们又有了一个客户端 1 ，
just put,
只是 put ，
draw a little bit more compact,
画得更紧凑一点，
because I don't have much space.
因为我没有太多的空间。
And you know we do a put,
我们执行一个 put ，
then we do, there's the read or a get,
然后我们做，一个读取或 get ，
get run returns 1,
get 返回 1 ，
so we're not in the first case,
所以我们不是在第一种情况下，
but in the second, but another case,
而是第二个，另一个案例中，
and then, we have to get that returns 0.
然后，我们 get 得到 0 。
And so that's the second sort of case that we looked at, correct,
这是我们看到的第二种情况，
this picture you know the back in time case.
在这张图片中，时间倒流的情况。
And again we can ask ourselves the same question,
我们再次问自己同样的问题，
is it allowed by linearizability?
它是否是线性一致性所允许的？
No, because the read wouldn't be return the value the last write.
不是，因为 read 不是返回最后一次写入的值。
Yeah, its pretty straightforward observation, correct,
是的，这是相当直截的观察，
this is absolutely not the case,
不是那种情况，
in fact, it's almost similar in the first case,
事实上，与第一种情况类似，
because these operations have to be in this order,
因为这些操作必须按这个顺序进行，
but you know that could not have happened,
但这是不可能发生的，
it would violate rule 3, right.
这违反了规则 3 。
Okay, so you know this gives you an intuition like linearizability means,
好的，这给了你关于线性一致性含义的感觉，
how you reason about it,
你如何考虑它，
and basically, if we don't do anything special,
基本上，如果我们不做任何特别的事情，
and we do this naive scheme,
我们做这个天真的方案，
if you were implementing lab 3,
如果你在实现实验 3 ，
and you followed this naive scheme,
你遵循这个天真的方案，
then you would not pass the test,
那么你不会通过测试，
because you know the test assume or the goal in lab 3 is
因为测试假设或实验 3 的目标是，
actually to provide linearizability for put and gets.
对 put 和 get 提供线性一致性。
And so the scenarios like these ones are just not allowed,
所以像这样的场景是不允许的，
you know your implementation has to be a in a way,
你的实现必须以一种方式，
that these results cannot appear.
这些结果不会出现。
Does that make sense?
这能理解吗？
So we're going lab 3 were a shoot for linearizability
所以我们要做实验 3 是关于线性一致性的尝试，
and what is one easy way of getting linearizability,
什么是获得线性一致性的简单方法，
how are we going to sure that puts or gets operation are linearizable.
我们如何确保 put 或 get 操作是可线性化的。
Well, I mean if you do actually we use one machine,
我的意思是，如果你真的用一台机器，
then it will be linearizable, right.
那么它就是可线性化的，对吧。
Yeah, so what's the easy solution,
是的，那么什么是简单的解决方案，
we run all the reads you know for the leader, right.
我们所有读取都通过领导者运行。
So basically the easy solution to get linearizability,
所以，获得线性一致性的简单解决方案，
and in fact, that's what we're gonna be doing in lab 3,
事实上，这就是我们在实验室 3 中要做的事情，
in lab 3 what going to be doing is
实验 3 要做的是，
you know read or get operations get ops go through the log,
读取或 get 操作操作要通过日志，
go through raft,
通过 raft ，
and as you observe,
正如你所观察到的，
it seems you know if they really go all through one machine,
如果它们都通过一台机器，
they might not go for one machine,
它们可能不是通过一台机器，
leader may change over time,
领导者可能会随着时间而改变，
when we know that the leader is always totally order, correct,
我们知道领导者总是有整体顺序，
the log is total order,
日志是有整体顺序的，
and so we're going to be able to construct you know a total order,
所以我们能够构建一个整体顺序，
that actually has the order matches real-time,
顺序与真实时间匹配，
and all the reads return values up the last write.
每个读取的返回值是最后一次写入的。
Because this is the raft protocol will guarantee,
因为 raft 协议将保证，
that all the entries in log are in a total order, right.
日志中的所有条目都是按整体顺序排列的。
And of course the raft protocol do quite a bit of work
当然 raft 协议做了大量的工作，
to actually make that all happen,
才能真正实现这一切，
and despite you know network failures,
尽管网络故障，
despite network splits,
尽管网络分裂，
you know the raft protocol will guarantee us,
raft 协议会保证我们，
that basically all the operations happen in a total order.
所有的操作都是按整体顺序进行。
In fact, the whole replicated state machine approaches are based on this idea, correct,
事实上，整个复制状态机方法都是基于这个想法的，
like all the ops in total order
所有操作在一个整体顺序中，
and applied in the same order all peers,
并以相同的顺序在所有节点应用，
and as a result, [] looks like a single machine.
结果，看起来像一台机器。
And so the easy way to solve this problem is
所以，解决这个问题的简单方法就是
to run all the reads you know through the leader,
通过领导者运行所有读取，
whenever the leader at that particular point of time
无论领导者在哪个时间点，
and that will give us linearizability.
这会给我们线性一致性。
Let me pause for a second, any questions about this?
让我暂停一下，有什么问题吗？
Sorry, matches real-time it just means that,
抱歉，匹配真实时间是意味着，
if operation 1 ends before operation 2 starts,
如果操作 1 在操作 2 开始之前结束，
then 1 before 2.
那么 1 在 2 前面。
Yeah, yeah, the raft,
是的，对于 raft ，
you know you will see that this will happen automatically, correct,
你会看到这是自动发生的，
because the the if operation actually completely finished,
因为如果操作完全结束，
that must have been the case,
肯定是这种情况，
that the leader responded you know back to a client,
领导者响应给一个客户端，
and then if the client started operation later
如果客户端开始操作较晚，
and must end up later in the log at the leader.
一定在领导者的日志中较晚。
So this is going to be a practice is true.
所以这是[真的]。
And also, so just double check, maybe reiterate,
而且，只是确认一下，也许重复了，
so the in lab 3,
在实验 3 中，
all of the client requests gonna be synchronous, []?
所有客户端请求都是同步的？
Yes it's absolute.
是的，确实是。
Okay, good,
好的，很好，
so you know what [] side of this scheme,
所以，[]所说的这个方案，
you know we'll go back actually,
我们回去，
if you read the raft paper very carefully,
如果你很仔细地看 raft 论文，
there's an optimization for read-only operations,
有一个针对只读操作的优化，
but even that optimization, requires some some communication.
但这个优化，也需要一些通信。
And so like if we just follow this naive,
所以，如果我们遵循这个天真的（想法），
you know this trick for a plan to actually get linearizability.
这个方案的[技巧]来获得线性一致性。
You know, does this what does that mean for performance,
这对性能意味着什么，
you know go back to sort of thinking about contrasting the zookeeper,
往回考虑一下对比 zookeeper ，
you know is for example,
比如，
the number of read operations is going to scale with the number of servers?
读操作的数量是否随着服务器数量的增加而增加？
No, because now everything has to pass through the leader.
不，因为现在所有的东西都要经过领导者。
Exactly, everything have go through the leader again,
没错，所有东西也要通过领导者，
so here we are again,
所以我们再一次，
that's a little bit undesirable, correct.
这不是我们希望的。
And so it gives you an instant question is,
所以它给了你一个即时的问题是，
like you know how is it possible,
这怎么可能，
that [when you go to] a zookeeper,
当你使用 zookeeper 时，
zookeeper gets great performance,
zookeeper 有很好的性能，
like we see the simple scheme that doesn't really work,
因为我们看到的这个简单方案并不起作用，
or at least violates linearizability.
或者至少违反了线性一致性。
And so one, so we want to talk a little bit,
所以我们想讨论一下，
like to understand what was really how did zookeeper get this.
理解 zookeeper 是如何做到的。
And so the first thing to really realize is,
所以首先要注意的是，
probably the most important part,
可能是最重要的部分，
is that zookeeper does not provide the linearizability,
就是 zookeeper 没有提供线性一致性，
it basically changes the correctness definition.
它改变了正确性的定义。
And so the zookeeper service,
所以 zookeeper 服务，
it's not going to behave like a single machine,
它的行为不像一台机器一样，
you know it's gonna have results that would never happen on a single machine.
它会产生在一台机器永远不会发生的结果。
So the particular, so what is it, what does it provide.
所以，它是什么，它提供了什么。
Well, it does provide linearizable writes,
它提供了线性化的写入，
so all the operations, all the write operation actually you know go through the leader
所以所有的写入操作都要通过领导者，
and you go through the log
通过日志，
and appended to the log every peer in the same order,
以相同的顺序写入到每个节点的日志中，
and so there going to also be applied in the same order,
所以，它们也将以相同的顺序应用，
so we still have this replicated state machine approach,
所以我们仍然有这个复制状态机方案，
where apply all the write operation,
应用所有写入操作，
operation change data into in the total order.
（应用）修改数据的操作以一个整体顺序。
But, there's a couple more properties.
但是，它还有几个特性。
So, but it does not provide linearizability for reads,
但是它不提供读取的线性一致性，
instead it sort of provides two sort of different property,
而是提供了两种不同属性，
which is that all the operations appear in FIFO order, in FIFO client order,
所有操作以 FIFO 客户端顺序出现，
this partly has to do with asynchronous,
这在一定程度上与异步有关，
you know client may submit multiple requests one by one
客户端可能会一个接一个地提交多个请求，
without waiting for a response.
而不等待回复。
And you know zookeeper will guarantee,
zookeeper 会保证，
if you submit client 1 submitted the request,
如果客户端 1 提交了请求，
and then client 1 submitted another request,
然后客户端 1 提交了另一个请求，
then that second request will appear later,
那么第二个请求将会较晚出现，
result will observe the result of the first operation.
（第二次）结果会观察到第一次操作的结果。
And so in particular you know writes goes client order,
所以，写入使用客户端顺序，
and then reads where all the actually is where the interesting properties are,
然后读取是我们感兴趣的性质，
the reads observe last write,
读取观察到最后一次写入，
okay, so reads reads observe last write from same client.
好的，读取观察到同一客户端的最后一次写入。
So this sort of makes sense,
所以这是有意义的，
you know basically this sort of sense like, you read your own writes,
就像读取你自己写的东西，
so if you do the write operation,
如果你执行写入操作，
you immediately follow the read operation,
你立即执行读取操作，
you see at least the results of your own writes.
你至少可以看到自己写入的结果。
But, for writes from other operations, from other clients,
但是，对于来自其他操作的，来自其他客户端的的写入，
the zookeeper does not guarantee that property,
zookeeper 不保证那个[性质]，
instead what it guarantees is that,
相反，它所保证的是，
the read will observe some prefix of the log.
读取会观察到日志的某些前缀。
And so this means right you can actually see stale data,
这意味着你可以看到旧的数据，
which may read from a follower
可能从一个跟随者读取，
and that follower has a prefix of the log,
那个跟随者有一个日志的前缀，
but not has the last entries in the log,
但没有日志中的最新条目，
because maybe just lag behind a little bit,
因为也许稍微落后了一点，
and nevertheless that follower is allowed to return a value,
尽管如此，跟随者允许返回一个值，
because you know the only thing that's you know zookeeper going to guarantee,
因为 zookeeper 唯一保证的事，
that actually reads observe a prefix log.
读取可以观察到日志的前缀。
So the operations can now go out of order,
所以现在操作可以不按顺序进行，
you know once they in the log,
一旦它们在日志中，
and you can sort of,
你不能，
reads can like read operation out of the log in out of order,
读取操作可以不按顺序，
it really has to be a prefix, a prefix of the log.
它真的是一个日志的前缀。
And then there's a second requirement,
然后还有第二个要求，
that you cannot do no reads from the past,
你不能从过去读取，
and it really means like if you saw some prefix 1,
这意味着如果你看到了前缀 1 ，
and then you issue reads some prefix one,
然后你发出读取前缀 1 ，
and then you read the second read,
然后你执行第二次读取，
then that second read has to see at least prefix 1 plus more.
那么第二次读取必须至少看到前缀 1 或更多。
It might be no, it might be just prefix 1,
它可能只是前缀 1 ，
but cannot go back in time,
但不能回到过去，
so it cannot see a shorter prefix than prefix 1.
所以它不能看到比前缀 1 更小的前缀。
And so this basically,
所以这个，
so so if we look back at this picture,
所以如果我们看回这张图，
the zookeeper will allow this in certain cases,
在某些情况下， zookeeper 允许这样做，
namely, if the two clients are different,
也就是说，如果两个客户端不同，
but it won't allow this,
但它不允许这样，
this you can never have back in time.
你永远不能回到过去。
Okay?
好的?
So I have a question, a conceptual one,
所以我有一个概念性的问题，
so we have these two consistency guarantees,
所以我们有两个一致性保证，
the linearizable writes and the FIFO client order,
可线性化写入和 FIFO 客户端顺序，
so if we ignore the second constraint for a second,
如果我们暂时忽略第二个约束，
and if we only focus on the first one,
如果我们只关注第一个问题，
does the definition of linearizable writes actually makes sense,
可线性化写入的定义真的有意义吗，
since the definition of linearizability
因为线性化的定义
depends on having a read operation and a write operation.
取决于具有读操作和写操作。
So you're like hold that thought for a second,
稍等一下，
because the way they define linearizable writes
因为，他们定义可线性化写入的方式
is not basically the writes in a total order,
不是写入在整体顺序，
and but there is a relationship between the read and the write,
但是在读取和写入之间存在关系，
so hold the thought for a second, okay,
所以稍等一下，
we'll come back,
我们会回来，
we get to that in a in a minute,
我们马上就到了，
like one board,
比如一个幻灯片，
I want to make one board in between, okay?
我想再说一个幻灯片，好吗？
Sounds good.
听起来不错。
Okay so, just like,
好的，就像，
let's look a little bit at
让我们来看看，
how zookeeper actually provides these guarantees.
zookeeper 是如何提供这些保证的。
And you know sort of get the intuition you know,
凭直觉来看，
how you could implement this,
你如何实现这个，
the paper actually not very explicit about how they implement this,
论文没有非常明确地说明他们是如何实现这个的，
sort of like I'm gonna give you a roughly best guess.
我会给你们一个大概最好的猜测。
So, there's a zookeeper client,
所以，这是一个 zookeeper 客户端，
it runs on the client machine,
它在客户端机器上运行，
in lab 3, we call this a clerk,
在实验 3 中，我们称它为 clerk ，
and so this is a piece of software library
所以这是一个软件库的部分，
sort of works collaborates with the service.
与服务进行协作。
In in zookeeper in the paper terminology,
在 zookeeper 论文术语中，
basically it is the thing that has session,
它是有个 session 的东西，
so when you join,
所以，当你加入时，
when a client wants to connect the zookeeper service,
当客户端想要连接 zookeeper 服务时，
you know it creates a session,
它会创建了一个 session ，
it connects using the session information to the leader
它使用 session 信息连接到领导者，
and maintains you know state across the session.
并在整个 session 期间维护状态。
So we have a leader in zookeeper,
所以我们在 zookeeper 中有一个领导者，
and we'll see you know followers,
还有跟随者，
you know basically this is all sort of similar,
基本上这有些相似，
to what we're used to from lab 2,
与我们在实验 2 中所做的，
and the zookeeper client issues write you know to the leader,
zookeeper 客户端发出一个写入到领导者，
because the writes are going to be linearizable,
因为写入是可线性化的，
in fact the writes basically follow
事实上，写入基本上遵循
exactly sort of roughly the same strategy as in the raft library,
与 raft 库中大致相同的策略，
so, it's going to be a log,
所以，会有一个日志，
and in the log,
在日志中，
all the writes are entered you know whatever you know some slots,
所有写入都会被记录到插槽中，
let's say the leader appends this write here in this particular index,
假设领导者将写入放到这个索引中，
so this has an index,
所以这有一个索引，
and in the paper, they refer to this index as zxid,
在论文中，他们将这个索引称为 zxid ，
so I think you can think about the zxid basically as the index in the log.
所以，我认为你可以将 zxid 视为日志中的索引。
And when the leader basically commits,
当领导者提交时，
an entry writes you know to the log,
一个条目写入到日志中，
it returns the zxid back to the client,
它将 zxid 返回给客户端，
so the client maintains that state,
所以，客户端维护该状态，
so associated with the session is basically with zxids zxid at last write.
所以与 session 相关联的是上次写入时的 zxid 。
Okay?
好的?
And so when the client later on the read,
当客户端稍后读取时，
and the read it doesn't have to go to the leader,
读取不一定要到领导者，
because that's the whole goal to get more performance,
因为这是获得更高性能的目标，
so maybe the read actually will go you know to one of the followers,
所以，读取可能会到其中一个跟随者，
and but then the read will be tagged with the zxid
但是，读取将使用 zxid 标记，
that of the last write that particular client is done.
那个客户端上次写入完成的（zxid）。
And so what does that mean,
那么这意味着什么，
well, let's say this following behind, right,
好的，假设这个在后面，
and it has two entries,
它有两个条目，
but hasn't actually observed you know the write yet,
但还没有观察到那个写入，
because whatever the leader may be committed it through these other followers.
因为领导者可能通过其他跟随者提交它。
And what happens in this case is that,
在这种情况下发生的是，
this read the follower won't really respond immediately,
这个跟随者的读取不会立即返回，
instead it will wait until the same you know the zxid,
而是等待相同的 zxid ，
and as soon as we've seen the zxid,
一旦我们看到了 zxid ，
it actually will respond.
它会做出回应。
Of course there's gonna be another client,
当然还会有另一个客户端，
and so maybe at some point this write will come through,
也许在某个时候，这个写入会通过，
and maybe now the read the client does another read,
可能那个客户端会执行另一个读取，
and so it hasn't seen you know other zxids,
所以它没有看到过其他的 zxid ，
and maybe like let me make one more follower,
让我再画一个跟随者，
let's say there's yet another follower,
假设这里有另一个跟随者，
that actually has not observed you know that that final write yet.
它还没有观察到最后一次写入，
Let me.
让我。
So there's going to be another,
所以还会有另一个，
let's say there's another client,
假设还有另一个客户端，
that sticks in some other write,
它执行其他一些写入，
that's the scenario I want to talk about,
这是我想要谈论的情景，
there was another client that actually appended w after the cxid,
还有另一个客户端将 w 附加在 cxid 之后，
you know it is right here,
就在这里，
but it was not observed that particularly write,
但还没有观察到那个写入，
you know what we have here,
我们在这里的，
is we got the, we got two slots,
我们有两个插槽，
we got to write,
我们要写入，
but you know the green write hasn't really show up at particular follower,
但是绿色文字还没有出现在这个跟随者上，
so if the client now issues second read,
所以，如果客户端现在发出第二个读取，
maybe that goes to the other follower,
也许它会传给另一个跟随者，
you know that's the same zxid,
这是相同的 zxid ，
because it hasn't seen any new,
因为它没有看到任何新的，
that client has not issued any new writes,
那么客户端没有发出任何新的写入，
it will arrive there,
它会到达那里，
and that guy is allowed to respond immediately,
而那个（跟随者）允许立即做出回应，
because it has seen the zxid of you know the [],
因为它已经看到了[]的 zxid ，
has seen the zxid of that particular client,
已经看到那个客户端的 zxid ，
of course, it misses some writes,
当然，它遗漏了一些写入，
you know that from other clients,
来自其他客户端的，
that are already being processed by some majority of the servers,
已经由大多数服务器处理的，
but it is not required to return that data
但它不需要返回那个数据，
and so it can just return.
所以它可以直接返回。
And so this might actually return in stale values,
所以，这可能返回旧的值，
but you know that allow by the definition of the zookeeper correctness guarantees.
但这是 zookeeper 正确性保证定义所允许的。
Professor, I had a question.
教授，我有个问题。
Yeah.
好的。
At first, I I thought, I'm not sure, but,
首先，我想，我不确定，但是，
I understood client reads like the session reads were sticky,
我知道客户端读取， session 读取是有粘性的，
so they would like in general go to the same.
所以通常它们会去一样的（节点）。
Yeah, you know but of course there might be a little bit of,
是的，但是，当然可能会有一点，
it might be a quick network partition or anything like it,
可能有一个快速网络分区或类似的事情，
and so in between time you know the,
所以在这中间，
it might have switched to another server.
它可能已经切换到另一台服务器。
Okay, and then.
好的，然后。
In addition, turns out the zookeeper does actually do some load balancing,
另外， zookeeper 做了一些负载均衡，
so but but nevertheless it can happen, right.
但是无论如何，这是会发生的。
Right.
是的。
The other thing was,
另一件事是，
you said write always always go to the leader,
你说写入总是到领导者，
and then the leader responded with zxid,
然后领导者用 zxid 回应，
that does the leader have to like first reach consensus before responding,
是不是领导者在回应之前必须先达成共识，
or in this.
或者类似。
Okay, yes, I guess so,
好的，我想是的，
you know that's committed, otherwise it is uncommitted, right,
它提交了，否则就没有提交，
I think the exact protocol,
我认为确切的协议，
I'm abstracting away a little bit in the details of the protocol,
我在协议的细节上做了一点抽象，
I'm just going to sketch how it works.
我只是大概描述一下它是如何工作的。
I believe you're right,
我相信你是对的，
you know that it must return presumably
它很可能返回，
after you know the entries really committed.
在条目真正提交之后。
Then, sorry last thing,
然后，抱歉，最后一件事，
you said it always goes to the leader,
你说过它总是到领导者，
but I think the paper described it could go to followers,
但我认为论文描述它可能会到跟随者，
so write go to a follower and then be read.
写入到跟随者，然后读取。
But then ends up to the leader, right,
但是最后回到领导者，对吧，
so it ends it go to the leader.
所以最终会到领导者。
Thanks.
谢谢。
Yeah.
好的。
Just to clarify,
只是确认一下，
when you say wait for zxid,
当你说等待 zxid 时，
like for example the second follower or second,
比如第二个跟随者，
when we wait for the zxid,
当我们等待 zxid 时，
we're actually waiting for it to be committed,
我们实际上是在等待它被提交，
it's not sufficient to just get.
仅仅[]是不够的。
It must be committed, yeah.
是的，它必须被提交。
Got it.
明白了。
Wait, but would like,
等等，但是，
it would have been committed by the time it was,
那时它已经提交了，
like a client wouldn't get an uncommitted zxid, right,
比如一个客户端不会得到一个未提交的 zxid ，
like ever, like.
像以前一样。
Oh, yeah, but just that's correct,
哦，是的，但这是正确的，
so if you know the this point,
所以如果这个点，
at this point, the follower sees zxid,
在这点上，跟随者看到 zxid ，
and the write is in that particular zxid,
写入在这个 zxid ，
now it must have been committed,
现在它肯定已经提交了，
because you know the client could not have gotten that zxid
因为客户端不可能获取那个 zxid ，
unless you know that that zxid was committed.
除非那个 zxid 已经提交。
Thanks.
谢谢。
Also, so when you say that from the read you you get stale data,
另外，你说读取到旧数据，
so like the last basic arrow,
就像最后一个箭头那样，
but the client here in the read request,
但是在读请求中的客户端，
it supplied these zxid within it,
它在提供了这些 zxid ，
so it's as if the client knowingly exactly wanted that location in the log,
就像客户端想要日志中的那个位置一样，
that had zxid as its index,
它以 zxid 为索引，
so didn't it knowingly just request that prefix that specific prefix of the log?
那么它不是故意请求日志特定前缀吗？
No, but really says you know what this zxid actually says,
不是，但是这个 zxid 实际上说的是，
like it's basically counters you know going back in time,
它是时间倒流的计数器，
and so the zxid like you know you have,
所以，你拥有的 zxid ，
as a follower, you have to return to your result,
作为跟随者，你必须返回到你的结果，
that at least concludes the prefix of the log through zxid,
至少通过 zxid [结束]了日志的前缀，
you might have more, that be fine too,
你可能会有更多，那也没问题，
but at least through zxid,
但至少到 zxid ，
and this just stops one case where you read back in time.
这阻止了你读取过去的情况。
Okay, awesome, thank you.
好的，太棒了，谢谢。
Okay, so now you might wonder,
好的，所以现在你可能会想，
you know, so this clearly does not provide linearizability,
这显然不能提供线性一致性，
and one reason people are excited about the linearizability is,
人们对线性一致性感到兴奋的一个原因是，
because it behaves like a single machine,
因为它的行为像一台机器，
so it's easier to program,
所以它更容易编程，
you know you do put, you do get,
你执行 put ，你执行 get ，
you roughly know what you're gonna get,
你大概知道你会得到什么，
and no pun intended,
没有双关的（返回），
but here you certainly have a model of programming model
但在这里，你有一个编程模型，
is different from a single machine,
不同于单一的机器，
and so you know how do you program this thing.
所以，你如何对这个东西进行编程。
And you know it turns out that,
事实证明，
there basically the rules,
这里的规则，
you know the correct definition that you know zookeeper has,
zookeeper 使用的正确性定义，
are basically you can think of it like,
你可以把它想象成，
those good enough to actually do for purpose to do help programming.
它足够好来达到帮助编程的目的。
And so I want to talk a little bit about that.
所以，我想谈一谈这一点。
So the real point is that,
所以真正的问题是，
you know with linearizability,
有了线性一致性，
it's pretty clear that you know that helps programming
很明显这有助于编程，
and writing intuitive programs,
以及编写直观的程序，
you think is going to be slightly different,
你的想法会有一点不同，
and we want to understand,
我们想要了解，
actually if things work out well,
如果事情进展顺利，
and whether it's like [] in the [] program
它是否像[]程序中的[]一样，
is basically completely unusable.
是完全无法使用的。
So, so let's look at one of the key examples they talk about in the paper.
所以，让我们来看看这篇论文中提到的一个关键例子。
And the first thing I want to do is,
我想做的第一件事是，
basically ignore the sync operation,
忽略同步操作，
because you can make every operation actually linearizable by just issuing sync,
因为你可以通过使用 sync 使每个操作线性化，
like before you do the read,
在你读取之前，
but that of course makes everything slow again,
但这当然会让一切再次变得缓慢，
and we're not going to get our performance,
我们得不到我们的性能，
so basically we want to avoid doing syncs,
所以我们想要避免使用 sync ，
and so I'm just gonna ignore syncs,
所以我要忽略 sync ，
and like program as if we don't have syncs.
像我们没有 sync 那样编程。
So let's look at the following operations,
那么让我们来看一下以下操作，
so here's the write order,
所以这是写入的顺序，
do a couple operations,
一些操作，
and this is the case of the ready file,
这是准备好的 ready 文件，
so we issue a delete of the ready file,
我们发出对 ready 文件的 delete ，
so, for example, this is a, a new master,
比如说，这是一个新的 master ，
that becomes, becomes the new, the new leader,
成为新的领导者，
and so need to write a configuration information in it,
所以需要在里面写入一个配置信息，
like you know who were part of the, the replicated state machine,
比如谁是复制状态机的一部分，
and who is the leader,
以及谁是领导者，
and so it writes you know some configuration files,
所以它写入一些配置文件，
write f1, write f2, create of ready,
write f1 ， write f2 ，然后 create ready ，
and then other followers,
然后其他跟随者，
might other is the read order,
其他可能是读取顺序，
they can you know for example call if exists ready,
它们可以调用 exists ready ，
and so zookeeper actually operation exists,
所以 zookeeper 执行 exists ，
and if ready exists,
如果 ready 已经存在，
then it will be a true,
那么这会是 true ，
and otherwise not and so you have to wait,
否则不是，你必须等待，
so let's ignore that case for a second,
所以让我们暂时忽略这个案例，
let's assume that you know the second clients,
假设第二个客户端，
so here was the one for one client did write operations,
这是一个客户端执行写入操作，
second client read operations,
第二个客户端执行读取操作，
and then if it exists,
如果它存在，
then the client reads f1 and then reads f2.
然后，客户端读取 f1 ，然后读取 f2 。
And so the thing that you know we want to understand,
所以我们想要了解的事情，
like you know what values could f1 this read actually return.
f1 这个 read 可以返回什么值。
The thing that we worry about correct is,
我们考虑的事情是，
it could return could return some result of a write,
它可能会返回之前写入的结果，
that was done much earlier here,
比这里还早的（写入），
or must have observe this write.
或者必须注意到这个写入。
I think the paper mentions that,
我想论文中提到了，
the reader can watch certain things
读取可以 watch 某些内容，
and be notified of changes.
并在变化时得到通知。
Yeah, so let's assume that actually the file exists,
是的，我们假设文件确实存在，
so created actually succeeds immediately,
所以 create 是立即成功的，
so let's talk about the notifications in a second.
我们稍后再来讨论通知。
So this exists returns immediately,
所以这个 exists 立即返回，
no watch evolved, it just exists,
没有使用 watch ，只是使用 exists ，
and then we do that second client does a read of f1.
然后第二个客户端执行读取 f1 。
I think it should read whatever was written by the first client,
我认为它应该读取第一个客户端写的东西，
because the operations are in FIFO.
因为操作是按 FIFO 顺序进行的。
Yeah, right,
是的，
so the I think the real thing that actually does.
所以我认为真正的事情。
If we saw this [] what value,
如果我们看到了这个值，
correctly for some write earlier,
对于前面的写入，
that would mean that we're reading back in time, right.
这意味着我们在回到过去，对吧。
And that is just not allowed,
这是不允许的，
you know the rules actually forbid that,
规则是禁止的，
this read you know must observe you know this value of that write,
这个读取必须观察到这个写入的值，
because this read the previous read exists observe this write, right,
因为这个 read 前的 exists 观察到这个写入，
so we know that you know this exists [id]
所以我们知道这个 exists id
must have seen the zxid corresponding by that create,
一定看到了这个 create 对应的 zxid ，
and so that means that,
也就是说，
this read will must you know must see the last write,
这个读取操作必须看到最后一次写入操作，
you know that was performed in the total order,
这是按照总的顺序进行的，
that proceeded you know that particular create,
执行这个 create ，
and so the last write you know critical order,
所以最后一个写入的关键顺序，
before that is this particular write, right,
在它之前是这个写入，
because all the writes are actually linearizable.
因为所有写入都是线性化的。
And so it must be the case,
所以，必须是这种情况，
that this read f1 observes the result of the write f1.
这个 read f1 观察到 write f1 的结果。
So this is nice, correct,
所以这很好，对吧，
because if you know some new leader became the primary,
因为如果某个新领导着成为了 primary ，
get raised configuration file,
得到一个配置文件，
you know we know for sure,
我们肯定知道，
that actually we're going to see that last configuration file,
我们将会看到最新的配置文件，
that was created by that by that new leader.
由新领导者创建的。
So we see here an example,
所以我们在这里看到了一个例子，
that these rules are carefully chosen,
这些规则是经过精心挑选的，
that you know things that you might care about,
一些你可能关心的事情，
if you're writing a configuration servers,
如果你编写一个配置服务器，
that actually certainly workout.
那么它确实是可行的。
Sorry, I I might have not understood what you were saying before,
抱歉，我之前可能没听懂你在说什么，
but in this case if it exists,
但在这种情况下，如果它存在，
if checking exists ready,
如果检查 exists ready ，
couldn't read like stuff before ready was deleted?
read stuff 不能在 delete ready 之前吗？
Okay, all the writes in the total order,
好的，所有写入都是按整体顺序的，
so these writes in total order,
这些写入按整体顺序，
that write is in total order,
那个写入按整体顺序，
that create in total order,
那个 create 按整体顺序，
so this read here on the other side has observed that create,
所以这个在另一边的 read 观察到那个 create ，
so whatever read is going to do is
所以不管 read 要做什么，
go back and in totol order, correct,
往回走，在整体顺序中，
like observed the last write in that total order,
在整体顺序中观察到的最后一次写入，
and at last write f1 is this one.
而最后写入 f1 就是这个。
But is exists writes?
但是 exists 是写入吗？
No, exists is read,
不， exists 是读取，
but exists observed this particular write.
但是 exists 观察到了这个写入。
Oh, you're saying.
哦，你是说。
You, you cannot read it back in time, correct,
你不能读取回到过去，对吧，
that just the whole goal.
那是总的目标。
Right, but how did we know that it observed, that exists.
是的，但我们怎么知道它观察到了，那个 exists 。
I told you that,
我告诉你，
I said like the file existed,
我说就像文件存在，
so it must be the case that it observed it,
所以，它一定是观察到了，
exists is return true.
exists 会返回 true 。
But it, but it existed before you deleted it, right.
但是它存在在删除它之前，是吧。
Yeah yeah yeah yeah,
是的，
but you know okay, we'll go back in a second,
但是，好的，我们一会儿回去，
let me, okay this is the second case,
好的，这是第二种情况，
this is a good point,
这是很好的观点，
let me a talk about that,
让我来谈谈这一点，
so there's another scenario,
所以还有另一种情况，
and I think this is the one you're worrying about that could have happened,
我想这就是你所担心的可能会发生的事情，
and this is where notifications come in.
这就是通知的作用。
So at least agree that this is right, correct.
所以至少同意这是对的，是不。
So the second case, more rules
所以第二种情况，更多规则，
and this is indeed interesting.
这是很有趣的。
I think the case where you're worried about is,
我认为你所担心的情况是，
here's our reader again,
这是我们的读取者，
here's our writer again,
这是我们的写入者，
and the reader you know calls exists on ready,
读取者调用 exists ready ，
unless the file you know is there,
除非文件在那里，
in you know does read f1.
执行 read f1 。
Alright, we're almost same as in the previous scenario,
好的，我们几乎和上一个场景一样，
and now like you know there's some changing leadership,
现在，领导权发生了变化，
you know there's a there's a crash, you know recovery,
这里有一个崩溃，恢复，
and all that kind of stuff is happening,
所以这类事情发生，
and so there's a new primary,
所以有一个新的 primary ，
it deletes ready,
它执行 delete ready ，
you know write f1, and write f2,
write f1 和 write f2 ，
and it's might create ready like as before.
它像以前一样 create ready 。
And let's assume that this like this read a little bit delayed,
我们假设这个读取有一点延迟，
and you know something else happened on the machine,
这台机器上还发生了其他事情，
and you know now does the read f2.
现在执行 read f2 。
And I think this is a very the question you were asking about,
我想这就是你所问的问题，
because this is the [] something, right,
因为这是[]的事，
because now there's a configuration change,
因为现在有了配置变化，
and if this configuration change gets flooded in the middle here, right,
如果这个配置更改在中间被[淹没]，
this read of f2 is going to return the new configuration,
这个 read f2 会返回新的配置，
as opposed to the read of f1 that is going to return the old configuration,
相反， read f1 会返回旧的配置，
and clearly things are gonna be messed up,
显然事情会变得一团糟，
that's not a scenario we want to be in,
这不是我们想要的情景，
so we terrible outcome.
所以结果很糟糕。
So and how does that actually you know get rectified,
那么，这是如何得到纠正的，
or how this actually zookeeper deal with this.
或者 zookeeper 是如何处理这件事的。
Well, this is where the watch come in,
好的，这就是 watch 的用处，
you know the pictures I drew in the previously board is not completely correct,
我在之前的白板上画的并不完全正确，
in addition to calling exists with the ready
除了调用 exists ready ，
is going to say watch to true.
还要设置 watch 为 true 。
And what that means is that,
这意味着，
this delete you know change is the ready file,
这个 delete 修改 ready 文件，
and we have now set a watch on the ready file,
我们现在设置了 watch 在 ready 文件上，
and so when the ready file gets deleted by this new primary,
所以，当 ready 文件被该新的 primary 删除时，
that actually results in a notification.
这会导致一个通知。
And there's a rule for this notification,
这个通知有一条规则，
and the rule for the notification is that,
通知的规则是，
every notification will be delivered before you know writes that go after it.
每个通知都在它之后的 write 之前发送。
And so what has to be the case,
那么情况会是，
that you know the this notification will be delivered before the write to f1.
这个通知将在 write f1 之前发送。
So when, so there's two possible scenarios,
所以，这里有两种情况，
if the notification gets delivered here,
如果通知在这里发送，
or the notification gets delivered like after the read of f2.
或者通知在 read f2 之后发送。
Let me move that read of f2 slightly up,
让我把 read f1 往上移一点，
or yeah,
或者是的，
so it's still happening,
所以，它仍然发生，
so in time behind you know the write operation,
从时间上来说，在 write 操作之后，
but notification gets [] delivered here depending on the delays
但根据延误情况，通知在这里送达，
or it's going to delivered here.
或者它会在这里送达。
Sorry, what's the exact wording of that rule that allows this to happen?
抱歉，允许这种情况发生的具体规定是什么？
Basically, I think one way to think about it,
基本上，我认为一种方式来考虑它，
the notification is like it was always like a write operation,
通知就像是一个写入操作，
and the followers you know implemented,
跟随者实现了，
so that the if the change happens to delete the notification goes off,
如果发生改变， delete 通知发出，
that notification is delivered to the client with that zxid.
通知会和 zxid 一起发送给客户端。
Yeah, but I still don't understand why this guarantees,
是的，但我还是不明白为什么这能保证，
that it can go like before,
它能到达之前，
wait, so the valid places for it are,
等等，所以它的有效位置是，
before the write of f1 and also like after the write of f2, right?
在 write f1 之前，也可以在 write f2 之后，对吗？
The notification is delivered after the after the delete of ready,
通知在 delete ready 之后发送，
and before the writes,
并且在写入之前，
before the writes of f1 and f2 are [],
在写入 f1 和 f2 之前，
or [in] the create for that matter.
或者在 create 。
Oh, I see.
哦，我明白了。
That's just a rule, zookeeper has to guarantee that.
这只是一个规则， zookeeper 必须保证这一点。
Okay.
好的。
Okay, so so that means there's two cases, correct,
好的，所以这意味着有两种情况，
like the notification gets delivered,
通知发送，
before the read of f1 or after the read of f1.
在 read f1 之前或 read f1 之后。
If we deliver, if it gets delivered after the read of f1 of f2,
如果它在 read f2 之后发送，
is there a problem?
会有问题吗？
No.
没有。
No, because then the read just happened before the writes.
没有，因为读操作就发生在写操作之前。
So everything's good,
所以一切都很好，
so this is this whole block is happening after the read of f2 is perfectly fine,
这整个块都发生在 read f2 之后，是可以的，
and how about here?
那么在这里呢？
Professor, did you say the watch is like a like write something?
教授，你是说 watch 就像写入某些东西吗？
Well, you can think about it,
你可以考虑一下，
the watch is not a write operation,
watch 不是写操作，
I didn't mean to imply that,
我并不是想表示这个，
the write, the watch is executed with the appropriate zxid,
watch 执行使用合适的 zxid ，
that's associated with that modification.
与这个修改有关。
Those are local, right, watches.
这些是本地的，对吗， watch 。
Yeah, the watches are local,
是的， watch 是本地的，
and so when they're executed,
当它们在执行时，
the it's guaranteed you know that they happened at the write,
保证它们发生在写入时，
when the write is observed
当观察到写入，
or the client sees that's [],
或者客户端发现[]，
the watch propagated with the zxid to the client
watch 传播 zxid 到客户端，
and make sure that execute it.
并确保执行它。
Thanks.
谢谢。
Again, the papers are slightly [vapor], exactly how it's implemented,
再说一次，论文有点模糊，关于它是如何实现的，
but you can imagine different scenarios,
但你可以想象不同的情景，
but the more important points like these rules guaranteed.
但重要的是这些规则是保证的。
Okay, so what happens if the notification is delivered here?
好的，那么如果通知送到这里，会发生什么？
So the client is running, correct,
客户端正在运行，
you know exists, the read f1
exists ， read f1 ，
and now this notification comes in.
现在通知来了。
Then you have to restart probably.
那么，你可能必须重新启动。
Yeah, you have to restart.
是的，你必须重新启动。
Okay? So what we see here basically is that,
好的？所以我们在这里看到的是，
you know the rules you know make programming definitely a bit more a difficult,
这个规则肯定会让编程变得更加困难，
but not impossible,
但并不是不可能，
you know with a little bit careful sort of programming,
只要稍加小心的编程，
you know you and understand the rules,
理解这些规则，
you can actually get the desirable results,
你可以得到想要的结果，
that actually probably the application wants.
可能是应用程序想要的。
What happens to the read f1 though?
read f1 发生了什么？
What happens to read f1?
read f1 会发生什么？
You start over.
你得从头开始。
Including that.
包括这一点。
Right.
是的。
Okay?
好的?
And you'll see this is a trick,
你会发现这是一个技巧，
that shows up in those [recipes] quite a bit,
在[]中表现得很明显，
like this there's an idea of actually you know bailing out and starting over again.
就像这个想法，跳出并重新开始。
Okay, so hopefully that gives you a sense that got for two things,
好的，希望这能给你两件事的感觉，
sort of even though people,
尽管人们，
one reason like people like linearizability is
人们喜欢线性一致性的一个原因是
because it's very intuitive,
因为它非常直观，
very easy to program with,
非常容易编程，
because everything behaves like a single machine.
因为每件事都像一台机器一样。
But if you want fault tolerance, scalability,
但是如果你想要容错，可伸缩性，
it's hard to get actually good performance,
很难得到好的性能，
and so one way to get good performance is
所以，获得良好性能的一种方法是
to compromise on the consistency guarantee,
在一致性保证上妥协，
and in this case,
在这种情况下，
you know compromising linearizability
对线性一致性妥协，
and provide some other consistency guarantee,
并提供一些其他的一致性保证，
and as we can see,
正如我们所看到的，
you know that's complicate the user experience of the programmer experience,
这让用户体验，程序员的体验变得复杂，
but, these rules in zookeeper are carefully chosen,
但是， zookeeper 中的这些规则是经过精心挑选的，
so still you know things can actually work out,
所以，事情仍然是可以解决的，
it's doable.
它是可行的。
So it is possible to get the write to sort of guarantees.
所以，它可能获得某种程度上的写入保证。
So now there's another aspect to this programming model,
所以，现在这个编程模型还有另一个方面，
and then I want to talk a little bit about now,
然后现在我想谈一谈，
that is really related to the coordination service part.
这与协调服务部分有关。
And so examples, you know that you need to,
比如，你需要，
you know what does it mean to be a coordination service.
一个协调服务指的是什么。
One good example is probably the VM virtual machine fault tolerance paper
一个很好的例子是虚拟机容错论文，
from a little while ago that we read,
我们不久前读过的，
and that had this test-and-set operation,
它有这个 test-and-set 操作，
the goal of the you know the test-and-set operation is
test-and-set 操作的目标是
basically make sure that there's no split-brain,
确保没有脑裂，
because basically two clients would run,
因为会有两个客户端运行，
and one would win the test-and-set, the other one wouldn't,
一个会赢得 test-and-set ，而另一个不会，
and as a result, you know the one that won the test-and-set
结果是赢得 test-and-set 的那个
could conclude you know that that's going to be the primary.
可以得出结论，它会是 primary 。
And so that is sort of a an example
所以，这是一个例子，
of feature that coordination service should be able to provide.
关于协调服务应该提供的特性。
And I wanna you know just just make a little bit more concrete,
我想让你，让它更具体一点，
let's think about with lab 3,
让我们来考虑一个实验 3 ，
could you get that with lab 3,
你能在实验 3 中获得它吗，
you know basically sort of test-and-set type thing.
一种 test-and-set 类型的东西。
Well, so let's do a very simple case,
好的，我们来做一个非常简单的案例，
you know let's say we have,
假设我们有，
here are simple implementation of test-and-set,
这是 test-and-set 的简单实现，
and in lab 3, we only have put and get operations,
在实验 3 中，我们只有 put 和 get 操作，
there's no other operations,
没有其他操作，
so those are the two operations,
这是两个操作，
so like how would you write this,
所以你如何编写这个，
you know, maybe you know do a put to a key, let's say master,
可能执行 put 到一个 key 中，比如 master ，
and we put my IP address in it,
把我的 IP 地址放进去，
the IP address of the caller
调用放的 IP 地址，
and then you do get,
然后你执行 get ，
you know and we say if the get on master is equal to my IP address,
我们说如果 get master 等于我的 IP 地址，
then you know act as master or act as leader.
然后知道作为 master 或者作为领导者。
Actually, this is our naive implementation,
实际上，这是我们天真的实现，
you know we don't have many other choices,
我们没有别的选择，
because we put, we only have put and get,
因为我们只有 put 和 get ，
and this is how we can implement this.
这就是我们可以实现这个的方式。
Will this do the desirable thing?
这会带来我们想要的结果吗？
Oh, there's no atomicity between the put and the get,
哦，在 put 和 get 之间没有原子性，
so maybe something changed.
所以，也许有些事情发生了变化。
Correct, so basically there could be two clients, correct,
对的，所以可以有两个客户端，对吧，
both could execute both put at the same time,
两个可以同时执行 put ，
and, and then observe, you know the,
然后观察，
in roughly, they could do it at the same time,
大体上，它们可以同时做这件事，
and the interleave correctly involve [actually]
而交错涉及到
return gets you know with their particular IP address, right,
get 返回它们的 IP 地址，
so we can get 2 leaders.
这样我们就得到两个领导者了。
And of course not what we want,
当然不是我们想要的，
so the main point of this,
所以这件事的要点是，
for example is basically you just have put and get,
比如，你只有 put 和 get ，
it's gonna be very hard to actually implement the test-and-set.
要实现 test-and-set 是非常困难的。
It turns out it's possible, but very complex,
事实证明，这是可能的，但非常复杂，
use bakery algorithm, you can actually probably do it,
使用 bakery 算法，你可能能做到，
but it's gonna be ridiculous,
但这是可笑的，
like to do that in a distributed system,
在分布式系统中这样做，
and so what zookeeper does,
所以， zookeeper 所做的，
it just provides some additional help,
它提供了一些额外的帮助，
to build the sort of [] primitives,
来构建[]原语，
we'll see in a second.
我们一会儿会看到。
The other thing that presumably what you want to know,
另一件事是你想知道的，
and lab 3 does not provide any support
实验 3 没有提供任何支持，
for you sort of configuration services or coordination services,
对你的配置服务或协调服务，
that you want to know when somebody goes down,
你想知道当一些机器宕机时，
for example you want to observe that
例如，你想要观察，
like the leader goes down,
比如领导者宕机，
like some other parties would like to know,
一些其他部分需要知道，
like is the leader down,
领导者宕机了，
so that we can choose a new one if it needed to,
我们就可以在需要的时候选择一个新的，
and so at least on the application of the building using a service.
至少在使用服务构建的应用上是这样的。
Okay, so, so there are two things that we really want,
好吧，我们有两个东西是真正想要的，
you know one is you know sort of way of trying to get this atomicity,
一个是试图使这个获得原子性的方式，
that's what we're looking for in the zookeeper design,
这就是我们在 zookeeper 设计中寻找的，
and then zookeeper design, second we were looking for in zookeeper design is,
然后我们在 zookeeper 设计中寻找的第二个是，
for an application to learn whether some node goes down.
让应用程序了解某个节点是否宕机。
So let's look at the zookeeper API,
所以，让我们来看一下 zookeeper API ，
and really we want to look at is znode API.
我们真正想要了解的是 znode API 。
And you'll see again,
你会再次看到，
that is actually carefully designed
这是精心设计的，
to actually make it possible
让它是可能的，
to do the things that we're we're looking for.
做我们正在寻找的事情。
Okay, so the way the system is organized is,
好的，所以这个系统的组织方式是，
you know there's a tree of znodes,
这里有一个 znodes 树，
typically you know there's like one sort of app1 as a znode,
通常情况下，有一个 app1 作为 znode ，
that might have some children,
可能有一些子项，
that correspond to the machines that are part of app1,
与 app1 中的机器相对应，
so it's like peer or machine 1, machine 2,
比如机器 1 ， 机器2 ，
like maybe IP addresses or DNS names,
比如 IP 地址或 DNS 名称，
machine 3,
机器 3 ，
and they might actually have version numbers associated
它们可能有关联的版本号，
or sequence numbers with them.
或者相关联的序列号。
And basically znodes can be of three types,
基本上， znode 有三种类型，
one, they can be regular,
一，它们可以是常规的，
so they're fault tolerance replicated all that kind of stuff.
所以它们的容错复制了所有这类东西。
And then they could be ephemeral,
然后它们可能是临时的，
and ephemeral basically means that the node will disappear automatically,
而临时意味着节点将会自动消失，
when the session with that the machine 3 goes away,
当机器 3 的 session 离开时，
so either because there's a network partition,
要么是因为网络分区，
there's no heartbeat more coming in from machine 3,
机器 3 没有更多心跳，
but at some point zookeeper decides you know that session is gone,
但在某个时候， zookeeper 认为时间已经到了，
and so then it will delete that node automatically,
然后它会自动删除那个节点，
and so that's where ephemeral nodes.
这就是临时节点。
And then there's a third one which is sequential,
然后第三个是顺序的，
oops, go back,
糟糕，返回，
to the third one you know type node sequential nodes,
第三个类型是顺序节点，
and that really means that,
这意味着，
you know that version version number associated with them in their name,
它们名字中与它们相关联的版本号，
and and they're created one by one in under particular znode,
它们是在特定的 znode 下一个接一个创建的，
all the children will have a sequence number in their name,
所有的子节点都在它们的名字中有一个序列号，
and the nodes are ordered by the sequence number,
并且节点按序列号排序，
and so again this might have sequence number 1,
这个可能是有序列号 1 ，
this might sequence number 2,
这个可能有序列号 2 ，
and this might have sequence number 3,
这个可能有序列号 3 ，
and the new one gets created will have a sequence number higher than 3.
而新创建的将会有大于 3 的序列号。
Okay, then, there's a API associated with that,
好的，有一个与之相关的 API ，
I want to talk a little bit about,
我想谈一谈，
there's create which we already mentioned a little bit,
有一个 create ，我们之前提到过，
you know takes a path, it takes some data and flags,
使用一个 path ，一些 data 和 flags ，
and the flags correspond to the three cases.
flags 对应于三种情况。
And then there's delete,
然后有一个 delete ，
and in the previous slide effort little bit misleading,
在上一张幻灯片中，有一点误导，
and delete takes a path before, it also takes a version number.
delete 使用一个 path ，以及一个版本号。
And exists takes a path and a watch.
exists 使用一个 path 和 watch 。
And then there's a getData primitive,
然后是一个 getData 原语，
takes a path and version number.
使用一个 path 和版本号，
And we'll see that these version numbers are the trick,
我们会看到这些版本号就是技巧，
are the key to actually get are atomicity.
是获得原子性的关键。
And then setData path data and version number.
然后 setData 有一个 path data 和版本号。
And there's also a call for getChildren
还有一个 getChildren 的调用，
to get actual the children of a particular znode,
可以获得特定 znode 的子节点，
which takes a path, and I think the watch.
它使用一个 path 和 watch 。
And there sync basically a call the operation
还有同步调用操作，
to actually ensure that actually,
为了确保，
so if you really need strong linearizability.
如果你真的需要强线性一致性。
Okay, so I want to talk a little bit about
好的，所以我想讨论一下，
you know why you know this version number handy,
为什么这个版本号是方便的，
and so, let's look at a particular example, the simple example,
所以，让我们来看这个简单的例子，
I can come up with basically implementing a counter.
我通常想出一个实现计数器。
And so the way you would write the,
所以你编写的方式，
if you write you know,
如果你编写，
okay so, let me actually first get the write solution,
好的，首先是写入方案，
so while you know true,
所以 while true ，
you know the way you implement increment,
你实现增量的方式，
so there's the pseudo code for increment of this counter,
所以这里是这个计数器递增的伪代码，
is you do get x,v you know getData of the counter,
你使用 x,v = getData 计数器，
getData count,
getData count ，
and then if you know setData count,
然后，如果 setData count ，
that's a sort of x+1 and the version number,
x+1 以及版本号，
and if that is the case, then break.
如果是这种情况，然后 break 。
Okay, so let me quickly go over this,
好的，让我快速回顾一下，
so the getData returns the current version number and the value of the key,
所以， getData 返回当前版本号和 key 的值，
so the key or the path you know,
所以 key 或 path ，
so for the file count,
对于文件数量，
it returns the value and its version number that particular point,
它返回当时的值和版本号，
when they did read,
当它们读取时，
and then you call and setData takes three arguments,
然后你调用， setData 接受三个参数，
you know the path, updates the new value,
path ，更新值，
in this case it's going to be x+1,
在这种情况下，它是 x+1 ，
because we want to increment the value by 1,
因为我们希望将值递增 1 ，
and it actually passes in the version number,
然后它传入版本号，
and the semantics of setData is that,
setData 的语义是，
if you know the version numbers are still the same,
如果版本号仍然相同，
then the setData actually happens and otherwise not.
那么 setData 发生，否则不发生。
So what does this protect against?
那么，这能防止什么呢？
This prevents you from interleaving the get-and-set, basically.
这可以防止你交错 get-and-set 。
So if like two operate, two clients did get at the same time,
所以，如果两个客户端在同一时间执行 get ，
they would read,
它们会读到，
they do get at the same time,
它们在同一时间执行 get ，
they get both back say you know whatever x 0 and version number 0,
它们都会获得比如 x 0 ，版本号 0 ，
x 0, version number 0,
x 0 ，版本号 0 ，
then they do both put,
然后它们都执行 put ，
where like in this case a setData,
就像本例中的 setData ，
so the setData with you know whatever x is 1, you know version number 0,
所以， setData 使用 x 1 ，版本号 0 ，
also this guy does the same thing,
这个也做了同样的事情，
set you know 1 0.
set 1 0 。
And you know why
你知道为什么，
and so both both clients issued two set operations,
所以两个客户端发出两个 set 操作，
both set operation []?
两个 set 操作[]？
Well, no.
没有。
And yeah, why not.
是的，为什么不。
Because one of the version numbers will be wrong.
因为其中一个版本号将是错误的。
Yeah, right, like so one of the two goes first,
是的，两个中的一个先执行，
why does one of the two go first?
为什么两个中的一个会执行？
Because all writes are linearizable.
因为所有写入都是线性化的。
Yeah, all writes are linearizable,
是的，所有的写入都是线性化的，
so they're going some total order,
它们使用一个整体顺序，
so you know we can pick one,
所以我们可以选一个，
so let's say this guy goes first,
所以我们假设这个先执行，
or this the operation goes first,
或者这个操作先执行，
so that will increase the,
所以这会增加，
that will increase the, the value correct 1,
这会增加值到 1 ，
from 0 to 1 is correctly
从 0 到 1 ，
and but will also and will execute,
而且也会执行，
because the version number is match, right,
因为版本号是匹配的，
like the version number 0 is actually what the current version number is,
因为版本号 0 就是当前的版本号，
so the version number match, the increment happens
所以版本号匹配，增加会发生，
and setData returns true.
并且 setData 返回 true 。
What will happen with the second one,
第二个会发生什么，
while the second one, the version number won't match,
第二个，版本号将不匹配，
because the version number will be increased,
因为版本号会增加，
because of previous setData operation,
由于之前的 setData 操作，
and therefore the second setData operation will fail,
所以第二个 setData 操作将会失败，
and so and then the client will loop back and try again,
然后客户端将会循环并重试，
and try to and try to take another shot and do the increment.
试着再做一次，执行增加。
And correct, so what happens in this case is correct,
所以在这种情况下发生的事情，
even though the two clients executed the operation concurrently,
即使两个客户端同时执行这个操作，
if the interleaving is bad,
如果交错不好，
you know the this piece of code will actually do the write thing,
这段代码会执行写入，
the second client will try again,
第二个客户端将重试，
and as a result you know the,
结果就是，
what the end value will be you know 2 supposed to 1.
最终的值会是 2 而不是 1 。
Okay?
好的?
Does that make sense?
这能理解吗？
If you've done any sort of lock-free programming in the past,
如果你在过去做过任何类型的无锁编程，
then this might now look very familiar to you,
那么你现在可能看起来很熟了，
and so this sort of style of lock-free
所以这种无锁的风格
basically zookeeper to encourage this sort of style of lock-free programming.
zookeeper 鼓励这种无锁的编程风格。
Okay, what I'd like to do,
好的，我想做的是，
since I'm running out of time,
因为我快没时间了，
last time I ran over time is,
最后时间，
I'll want to talk with some points about logs,
我想谈几点关于日志的问题，
but I will do that next time,
但我会在下次这么做，
the next lecture.
下一节课。
Now let me just sort of summarize what we've learned so far,
现在让我来总结一下，我们到目前为止所学到的东西，
and then I'll talk a little bit more about zookeeper in the next lecture.
然后我将在下一节课中更多地谈论 zookeeper 。
So, as summary,
所以，作为总结，
so basically you know just a very successful design,
所以这是一个非常成功的设计，
widely used,
被广泛使用，
you can download you know on github,
你可以在 gitHub 上下载，
you can play around with it, if you wanted to,
如果你想的话，你可以玩它，
and one of the things that's interesting about it,
其中有趣的一点是，
compared to all the systems that we look so far,
与我们目前看到的所有系统相比，
it has weaker consistency,
它的一致性较弱，
which weaker consistency, I mean it doesn't provide linearizability,
较弱的一致性，我的意思是，它不提供线性一致性，
and you know we're seeing that basically as a careful design API,
我们看到一个精心设计的 API ，
at least we've seen some aspects of the careful design API,
至少我们已经看到了精心设计的 API 的某些方面，
that despite the fact that actually has weaker consistency,
尽管它具有弱的一致性，
you can still use it,
你仍然可以使用它，
and in fact you know you can use it actually for pretty important applications,
事实上，你可以把它用在非常重要的应用上，
you can actually use zookeeper as a configuration service,
你可以将 zookeeper 用作配置服务，
like its main purpose of keeping track of,
比如它的主要目的是跟踪，
like who's primary, who's in the, who what the set of replicas etc etc,
比如谁是 primary ，什么是复制等等，
and so for this sort of crucial operation of being a configuration service,
所以，对于这种作为配置服务的关键操作，
that has to be correct,
这必须是正确的，
because otherwise we get to split-brain problem,
因为否则我们就会有脑裂的问题，
the API carefully designed,
API 精心设计，
so that if you use the API correctly,
所以，如果你正确使用 API ，
you still can implement this crucial application on top of it,
你仍然可以在其上实现这个关键的应用程序，
despite the fact that actually provides weak consistency.
尽管这提供了弱一致性。
And the cool part of that is that,
最酷的是，
this discrimination,
这种区别，
you know like sort of careful design API and the weaker consistency
精心设计的 API 和弱一致性，
allows us to get you know zookeeper really high performance.
允许 zookeeper 获得高性能。
And we'll see later in later lectures,
我们将在后面的课程中看到，
more of this sort of trick,
更多这种技巧，
of trying to weaken the consistency guarantees
试着减弱一致性保证，
to actually you know get better for get better performance
为了获得更好的性能，
or you know able to continue despite network partitions.
或者即使网络分区，也能够继续。
Okay, let me stop here,
好的，让我停在这里，
and then I'll resume in a little while,
然后我会继续一段时间，
the next time around for the [] lecture.
下一次[]课程。
Any questions?
有什么问题吗？
Where again as usual,
像往常一样，
if you have to go, please feel to go,
如果你一定要走，请随意，
if you want to hang around and ask more questions,
如果你想留下来问更多的问题，
you know feel free, please feel free to do so.
也请随意提问。
Sorry, can you go to the slide which said the set,
抱歉，你能看一下幻灯片，
the unsuccessful example for the set and for the test-and-set,
test-and-set 的失败的例子，
I think it's two slides back.
我想是倒退两张幻灯片。
This one?
这一张?
Yeah, so the new design,
是的，所以新的设计，
it's, it is able to fix that write.
它能够修复那个写入。
Yeah, I mean like API zookeeper provides.
是的，我的意思是 zookeeper 提供的 API 。
In the [] version write.
在[]版本写入。
Yeah, if you have to exactly,
是的，如果你必须这么做，
I didn't get to do that,
我没有这么做，
but that was going to the rest of the lecture is to talk about,
但这将在课程的其余部分讨论，
how you can implement test-and-set using the version numbers.
如何使用版本号实现 test-and-set 。
And clearly the increment suggests you can, correct,
很明显，增量表明你可以，
because this is basically the same sequence.
因为这是相同的序列。
Right.
是的。
Oh, if this is the same thing as the master, okay.
哦，这和 master 是一回事，好的。
Yeah, that exactly.
是的，就是这样。
Okay, thank you so much.
好的，非常感谢。
You're welcome.
不客气。
I have a question about this version versioning to prevent lock
我有一个关于防止锁的版本，
to implement lock-free programming,
为了实现无锁编程，
is this like much more efficient lock-free programming,
这是不是像更高效的无锁编程，
because you still need to read,
因为你还需要读取，
try the operation again and again
反复尝试那个操作，
until it succeeds write.
直到它成功写入。
Yeah, again, this test-and-set has a similar property, correct,
是的，这个 test-and-set 有类似的属性，
if the test-and-set failed,
如果 test-and-set 失败了，
and you wanted to become you know actually increment,
你想增加，
you have to do that again,
你必须再做一次，
so, it's often the case,
所以，通常是这种情况，
in this lock-free style programming,
在这种无锁风格的编程中，
that you have these loops where you retry.
你有这些循环，用来重试。
And so if there's a lot of contention,
所以，如果有很多[争论]，
you're gonna get a lot of retry,
你会有很多次重试，
because there's no contention, there's no retry,
因为没有争用，所以没有重试，
and typically you know these lock-free algorithms actually are pretty careful
通常情况下，这些无锁算法都很小心，
in how they do the back off,
在如何进行后退方面，
so they don't really retry immediately,
所以它们不会立即重试，
you know they have some backup plan.
他们有后备计划。
Right, but what benefits this skip over a standard lock,
好的，但这比标准锁有什么好处，
because either way if you have a lot of contention,
因为无论哪种方式，如果你有很多争论，
you're gonna be like sitting there and retrying a lot.
你会在那里并反复尝试。
Yeah, so let's,
是的，所以让我们，
yeah, so you know,
是的，所以，
so, the increment counter is an example,
所以，增量计数器是一个例子，
where basically sort of implicitly do the locking,
隐式地执行锁，
because you will see if we implement locks in zookeeper,
因为如果我们在 zookeeper 中实现锁，
like zookeeper, implement locks with zookeeper API,
使用 zookeeper API 实现锁，
and then if you do this stupid lock,
如果你用这个愚蠢的锁，
you can also have this contention issue,
你也可能会有这个争执的问题，
of course, there's a way of implementing smarter lock,
当然，有可以实现更智能的锁的方法，
they talked about like without [hurting]
他们无伤大雅地谈论着，
and then you could do better,
然后你可以做得更好，
and so I hoping to talk about next time.
所以我希望下一次能谈到。
Okay, thank you.
好的，谢谢。
I think the real point here is you know that,
我认为真正的问题是，
you can use these primitives to actually do lock-free programming,
你可以使用这些原语来进行无锁编程，
like with the interface that the lab 3 provides, its not possible.
而使用实验 3 提供的接口是不可能的。
Makes sense, thank you.
理解了，谢谢。
Any further questions?
还有什么问题吗？